hello and welcome this is active
inference guest stream number 43.1 it's
May 11 2023 and we're here with Tom
Frost
today we're going to be talking about
the paper eruption Theory a novel
conceptualization of the inactive
account of motivated activity
we're going to walk and talk through the
paper and there will be a lot of time
for questions so please feel free to add
any in the live chat thank you Tom for
joining and to you for an introduction
and overview
okay thank you
um so yeah hello everybody
um my name is Tom Frost I'm the head of
the body cognitive science unit at the
Okinawa Institute for Science and
Technology Graduate University in Japan
and
um the scientific mission of her unit
overall is to take the advances the
theoretical advances in cognitive
science that are sometimes brought
together under four recognition so
that's embodied embedded extended and
active approaches to cognition which to
our minds are on the right track in
terms of how we should think about the
mind and how it relates to the world but
so far I haven't gotten a lot of
exposure and experimental work
um and so our unit is basically trying
to become an interface where we can do
exciting work on the theory side of
things and then try them out and
experimental work and we have work on
human computer interaction we have
um uh EEG brain Imaging we do sensor
substitution research
um there's all kinds of stuff about
behavioral coordination and social
settings and haptics and
um and so
um it's very exciting place to be
because we're kind of sticking our necks
out a little bit and saying you know do
all these cool ideas that you know love
and cherish actually make a difference
in how you know science is done in the
lab and that's you know that's why we're
here but at the same time uh what what
that kind of ambition makes clear is
that some of the theoretical work also
needs to adapt and change and and
Advance such a more directly connects
with the kind of things that we can do
experimentally
and so the current paper that we're
going to discuss is one of those
outcomes where I'm trying to think a
little bit more clearly about how we can
operationalize some of the ideas that
are coming out of the inactive approach
such that we can start thinking about
how to formalize them and how to even
measure them using something like you
know analysis of EEG signals
awesome very cool
theory and practice and um there's a lot
of prose papers and a lot of philosophy
and so it's just very exciting even with
the Technologies you mentioned like how
this really comes into play and how it
does make a difference so
what's the story with this paper how did
it come to be and where does it fit into
that broader work of the group
yeah sure so
um let's zoom out just a little bit
before I go to the specific paper so for
most of my career
um I've been working on work like
because like Origins you know origins of
Life origins of mine origins of social
cognition origins of social complexity
um and I think that kind of look at
Origins is share quite widely among my
colleagues so what we want to understand
is what are the conditions the necessary
and sufficient conditions for there to
be a living being or there to be Agency
for there to be sense making or
participatory sentence making
um and so for most of my career I've
been looking at other you know
developing ideas about what are those
conditions
and in the background there was always
this assumption that that's pretty much
all the work that we need to do in order
to have a cohere notion of let's say
agency
um in the sense that uh Notions such as
active versus passive
um or going back to avanoi's famous book
action and perception which was like you
know the super hot book when I was a PhD
student and it was discussed so widely
we never really questioned what is the
action part of this uh so how do we
Define something as being active versus
passive
um yeah there are some ideas about
regulation and normativity things can go
wrong and right when there's action in
play and intentions in play
um but to really think about how those
intentions and values could make a
downstream difference to let's say the
neurophysiology composition of the body
is something that we just left to the
side and didn't even really consider us
part of the problems that we had to
solve
so
um somehow uh doing the attempts at
modeling this uh so another stream of my
research is an agent-based simulation
model where we try to look at the
minimal dynamical conditions that lead
to a certain kind of behavior so let's
say
I can ask what is the minimal setup that
I need in order to study social
contingency where One agent is sensitive
to the dependence of the others movement
on its own movement
and I can do that and you can analyze
that and I can evolve it and I can study
the state space of it
um and and then we we thought kind of
like our job is done you know we've
understood the Dynamics of it and now
let's move on to the next problem
um but something started bugging me
about that when I tried to more
integrate that kind of work with my
interest in phenomenology and this goes
back to uh Francisco varela's work and
neurophonology where he proposed that
dynamical systems theory could be the
kind of formal bridge between on the one
hand a kind of Australian style analysis
of immunology and on the other hand
empirical work in Neuroscience primarily
but also including the body and
interaction with the world and so his
idea was that because dynamical systems
theory doesn't make any ontological
commitments about what it is that's
changing in time all it is doing is
describing how something is changing in
time it can equally be applied for
mental processes which change in time
and physical processes which also change
in time and then the the challenge is
just to find a kind of general form or
structure which integrates both of these
processes changing in time and voila
we've solved the mind-body problem you
know I'm simplifying but that does kind
of like the general ambition right so
um I'm not a neuroscientist by training
so so I did the best thing I could which
is work more at the level of modeling
the behavior of systems but again the
ambition was if I can create a dynamical
systems model of something like social
contingency then on the one hand I can
connect it with something happening in
feminology and on the other hand I can
make a hypothesis about what would be
necessary or sufficient in terms of
experimental work
the problem is that that kind of work
after a while made it very clear that
um the dynamical systems approach didn't
leave any room
for anything else to make a difference
other than the equations that I was
putting into the model which is to say
that you know as long as I knew the
initial conditions of my simulation and
as long as I knew the equations that
determine how stage change over time all
the rest is already predetermined I can
exactly replicate again and again by
just resetting this relation
so it unfolds over time in a
predetermined way sometimes we cannot
predict it in advance so it's not
necessarily predictable without you
running it but it is repeatable and
identical way so there's nothing
happening in each time steps so to speak
that could ever be surprising once
you've seen the whole thing unfold
and so that really started bugging me
because why I got interested in the
inactive approach originally
is because it was all about action and
perception it was all about agency it
was all about intentions and sense
making that meaning makes a difference
to how we behave in the world
um uh you know what happened to the
values or like you know we were always
talking about that you know the inactive
approach has an account of how values
can be intrinsic to the organism because
of its precarious self-production and
this goes into the direction about the
creases and so on
but here I was confronted with the with
the fact that if we describe all of that
in dynamical systems theory there's
actually no room for values to make a
difference everything is already
predetermined by the Dynamics
um and so in unpacking that
dissatisfaction a little bit eventually
resulted in a complete turnaround where
I now reject
um the adequacy of a purely dynamical
systems approach to describing phenomena
that have to do with agency and sense
making and meaning and value which in
this paper are basically a group under
motivations there's something else
making a difference to how the agent is
behaving over time
so so that's the kind of like background
story and uh I have to say that it took
me maybe three years to get myself to
this point because it's a big break in
my own thinking and what I've written in
the past and
um you know at this point I'm not sure
how many of my colleagues are actually
on board with this change
um so it's kind of like exciting and
nerve-wracking at the same time to say
like you know mid-career changed that
suddenly throws out a lot of what has
gone in the past but uh you know this is
why we do science right sometimes you
have to change your mind and so what we
can do today is that I will talk to you
a little bit through this paper and you
can probe it and uh you know who knows
eventually I might change my mind back
and say actually this is not correct
right but right now I I think this is
you know the way that we should move
forward and there's a lot of rich like
implications to further unpack and so
so yeah personally I'm super excited
um that that you know that I had this
change of mind about how to think about
the relationship between mind and body
um and I think it's going to be
um you know helping to some extent
inactive cognitive science or embolic
recognition more generally to live up to
its own expectations that it has
something serious to say about how
things like meaning and value make a
difference to behavior
wow is that right for the context should
I jump into the the paper oh it's it's
quite a saga thank you for sure sharing
that really helps a lot so into the
paper we go
okay all right
so
um
right so maybe clarification so
motivated activity by the way can you
see my cursor or uh yes we do okay all
right so motivated activity is the term
I'm going to use
um to capture all of these other aspects
I was talking about so meaning value
intentions it could also be higher level
Concepts like beliefs desires
so anything that has
um a kind of like Asian level uh
Association
um and which is not just uh if you use
Stuart Kaufman's terms just a mere
happening so something is doing
something uh and that kind of brings
with its normative criteria of either
succeeding or failing or being good or
bad at whatever it is that needs to be
done so it's a kind of quality of the
difference to just mere activity
um so because I was you know I need a
term that captures all of that vast
diversity of possible normative behavior
and then here I'm just gonna say the
activity is motivated by something else
and that something else will be one of
these uh agent level uh Concepts nice so
it's supposed to be a very broad Theory
it just makes me think of how an
enzymatic reaction could be catalyzed
but it wouldn't necessarily be motivated
whereas motivation for an agent could be
a catalyst yeah yeah so uh and here I
don't go into this but the kind of in
the background there's the idea that
um the next one of the next steps will
be to generalize this into a notion of
biological regulation
um and so there's a lot of Life Sciences
happening here at my University
um and if you talk to them you know they
they basically treat their systems as
mere happenings right it's as it was
just a pretty physical system without
any motivated activity but I'm not sure
that that's the right way of thinking
about it so when a cell does something
for a reason like up or down regulating
things possibly this account also
applies there because then Notions of
success and failure and how much and how
little is you know the right amount and
so on start making a difference of life
and death sometimes and so we should
expect something similar to be happening
even at that kind of low scale level so
although I'm gonna unpack it now in
terms of the human level because that's
the most intuitive level
um I think that the general principles
in the background apply to all kinds of
Regulation even unconscious biological
resolution
all right and just I'm sure we're gonna
go into it but what is the etymology of
eruption
right I mean we can already uh get into
this uh now we're given that we're
already kind of uh into the kind of
contextualizing part
um so some of the influences that uh
have been very impactful for me uh go
back to cybernetics and particularly the
work of Ross Ashby
um and he has this notion of ultra
stability which is supposed to be a way
of explaining how can a system
uh become stable after being perturbed
out of that stability in a spontaneous
self-organized way without actually
having any kind of like top-down
explicit knowledge of what it is that's
going wrong or how it should do to fix
it
um and so again it's supposed to be a
generalizable account of biological
regulation
um and you know most work back in the
day was taking the opposite extreme of
saying Hey I want to have perfect
information about my target I want to
have perfect information about my error
and then I want perfect information
about how I should reduce that error in
order to hit my target right and that's
kind of like control theory feedback
based control theory
um and we can engineer systems like that
but nature is messy and a lot of the
times you know whatever hits the system
you don't know what it is that's hitting
it you just know that something is not
quite right and so Ashley basically
proposed that as long as the system is
able to break
and this gets close to eruption
um that break basically means a change
in its structure or a change in its
organization and that basically means
that as long it's not dead after that
break it has a chance to have hit on the
configuration that actually is a the
right kind of response to whatever is
perturbing it it's a new kind of
organization so it could be a stable one
and if it's not stable then it will
break again
until it eventually hits another
configuration and which it doesn't break
anymore and it has basically found a new
pocket of stability right so it's kind
of like a example of stochastic search
um but you know the the interesting part
is that for Ashby
um this break comes from the outside
it's like you know he has this example
of a kitten being burned by by the fire
and it's far it touches the fire it you
know it gets burnt and it has to learn
not to touch the fire anymore
right so if there is no breaks happening
according to Ashby the system wouldn't
do anything it would just be static to
some extent it would just maintain its
identity and sit there and so something
perturbs it in the right way and then it
would react and so
um for me that was always kind of like a
very strange way of looking at life I
mean that view maybe applies to
something like a computer that if you
don't touch it it just doesn't do
anything and then if you do something to
it it will respond
but living systems are somehow
intrinsically active right so they're
always doing stuff uh they're always
changing adapting developing evolving
learning
um right and so uh the idea that they
are just uh that all of those changes
are only responses to the environment
rather than something that is
intrinsically driven doesn't make much
sense to me there must be also something
on the inside of the organisms that
makes them Restless in a way and so one
of the early attempts at getting at that
was to think of a notion of
self-breaking what if actually systems
continuously break themselves a little
bit which basically then has the
consequence that the organization slowly
also changes over time and so then they
are no longer dependent on their
environment for adaptation but this
basically becomes an intrinsic source of
adaptation and so this notion of
eruption goes back to Latin which is the
kind of like sudden breaking into or
meaning of breaking actually and then
kind of internal break in the system
all right so into the into the paper
um so like I said uh is you know the
main motivation is getting a grip on
what do we mean by action
um and like that's one of the concepts
that goes back to the 90s right I mean
like if you think about the embodied
mind the classic text by uh Varela at
all
um you know the way they Define uh the
inactive approach is basically by
linking action and perception into a
loop
um but what is action uh can a robots
perform an action uh is it enough that
there's just mere movement
um and this is a long debate also with
ecological psychology is it necessary
that this movement originates in the
organism or could it also be something
that happens from the side of the
environment as long as it's a relational
change and so on
um and so basically uh I I argue that I
don't have a really good grip on what do
we mean by action
um when and when an agent makes a
difference
um and so
I review the inactive approach
um not sure how much I should go into
this maybe just to say uh briefly
um so this is what I meant in the
beginning where most of the work of the
inactive approach has focused on the
emergence of living beings with an
intrinsic perspective of concern
um uh with sense making capacities and
so on rather than the downstream
consequences of when that is actually in
place but just briefly the idea is that
um when we attribute purpose
to an artificial system we can do that
right the function of a car is a drive
and if it doesn't drive it's broken so
there's a normativity there we have a
criteria for evaluating if it's doing
the right or the wrong you know function
um no organism seems to be of a similar
kind we can also look at an organism and
say you know is it behaving
appropriately or not giving it
circumstances in its environment and if
it's not uh well that's pathology that's
a disease that's sickness and so this is
actually you know at the core of
medicine to some extent if he didn't
have any criteria for distinguishing
when things go right and when they go
wrong well how could we ever try to heal
someone right so intuitively we have
we're working with these Concepts
already
um so the inactive approach the idea is
that basically the main difference
between a car and an organism is that
the car is produced from the outside
whereas the organism produces itself
from the inside so there's a network of
processes of material production which
basically create and synthesize all the
molecules that compose our bodies and
those molecules of our bodies are
exactly the ones that permit the
reactions to proceed in building the
body so there's a kind of
self-referential self-referentiality in
the way in which we are organized and
because of this self-reference the
functions that we that the body is doing
are actually created by the body itself
that means they are intrinsic to the
body and so the idea is that this is
kind of the way in which we can move
from just a purely external attribution
of value and purpose and you know
classic teleology to some extent to
understand intrinsically based one
because of the salt production of the
organism and there's one additional
Point here so this would be a way of
saying the goals are intrinsic but then
there's also the question like why would
anything matter to the organism in the
first place right and this is another
important difference between life and
let's say machine like a car if the car
doesn't work it doesn't care about that
it doesn't work right it's just as happy
if I can say that to not be working
compared to working it makes no
difference to the car very different for
organisms they will be processes uh
coming in active when things don't go
right right so in order to try to
compensate somehow
and so the idea is that because the
living organism's being it's very
existence depends on these active
processes that's why things matter to it
it's because the organism itself is its
own creation so to speak
um and and not something that is just
created from the outside
um and so this is why precariousness as
a notion is so important for the
inactive approach that given that it's
an active process that's taking place
under precarious condition which means
that if the processes are stopping or
not proceeding in the right way the
entire being of the organism would just
cease
uh that means the being depends on the
actions of the organisms and hence the
outcome of those actions matter to the
organism that's why it has an intrinsic
perspective of concern on its
environment and that's where meaning
comes from that's why the World shows up
as mattering to us and to organisms
right so that was a kind of mini summary
of I don't know two decades of inactive
work on on
um you know sense making so
um did that make sense to you otherwise
I can go a little bit further here but
um I think this work has been you know
much discussed already so maybe we
yeah we can we can we can return but
please continue
okay all right
so uh here's a couple of diagrams of
what does this mean in terms of thinking
about uh how value could make a
difference so if you've got this uh
paper from I think back in 2010 by the
part of it all where uh once you start
thinking about value or something
intrinsic to the organism and as tied to
its process of cell production
you start to see that how other people
use the notion of value in cognitive
science can be quite different and so
the diagram on the left where we have a
value-guided learning
shows the way in which many
architectures in cognitive science think
of value which is basically is a kind of
evaluation system so there's a kind of
sub-component somewhere in your
cognitive architecture and the task of
that subcomponent is to make some sort
of judgment about the situation in the
world and then pass the outcome of that
judgment to in this case the behavior
generating system
and so the critique that the authors do
of this is to say well you know you can
call this a value system but you could
call it anything you want to some extent
you know you can call it like uh
um I don't know decision system you can
call it uh um a comparator system or or
whatever
um but there's nothing intrinsically
different about the functions that it
does to some other function in the in
this architecture so there's nothing
qualitatively different about the kind
of behavior the sub component realizes
and it's very localized so there's a
worry that maybe what's going on here is
that there is an unjustified
verification of value into something
concrete and specific inside this
component and so their alternative
proposal On The Rise is that value is
something that emerges out of these
self-producing self-regulating processes
of the organism and somehow shape that
those processes uh in the background
and
so I think this has been kind of like
the standard way of thinking about value
for maybe the last 10 years or so on the
inactive approach and it's something
that you know I was also in that
tradition and now I'm just one way of
thinking about what I'm doing now is to
really ask the question well even if a
value would be an emergent property
rather than a local concrete property
there's still the question of how does
that value actually make a difference
uh to the processes you know if we
remove this word value from our diagram
would it make any difference
and so what I said before about my
simulation models is that I mean I don't
see any difference right so I can just
run my agent-based simulation models and
then I can say oh this emerging property
here I want to call that you know the
value of going towards the goal or
something like that
but the system doesn't care about that
attribution I mean you know I could also
not call it that or I could call it the
value of being happy and the behavior of
the system would be exactly the same it
just makes no difference to the Dynamics
of the system
and so
um
what what are the options uh you know
how do we integrate this notion of value
into our scientific account of behavior
just just one one note on this
um on on figure one
um the left side is very compatible
maybe even isomorphic with the
reinforcement learning computational
architectures where you have some
behavioral selection module like you
mentioned and then there's like a
secondary evaluation that's like
annotating or layering over the process
of behavior being generated
but at least value plays a specific
semantic role whereas as as
um shown here it values everything then
it's nowhere you know if it's in the
foreground it's in the background and um
you have a closed loop and you have no
need to explain anything further so you
might as well just add all kinds of you
know draft manuscript not for
circulation and this is how organisms
work you can add all kinds of things but
that's not going to break the closure
of the self-sustaining dynamical
processes in the world and that closure
has been highlighted by
um a lot of the work you've described
recently as well as Kant and others who
are described in the manuscript
yeah so
um that's right and like you know when
we ask ourselves why is the inactive
approach of value not more successful
even though it's somehow compelling in
its biological grounding I would say
it's precisely because it doesn't give a
better account of the efficacy of value
right so yeah maybe the the traditional
account has a set of problems such as
like you know where do these values come
from in the first place you know if they
can just be captured by functions you
know do we lose somehow the qualitative
aspect of them and so on but at least
they do work right I mean at least they
have a function in the architecture
that's very specific and formalizable
and can be implemented in these kind of
for example reinforcement learning
paradigms
um whereas like the inactive notion is
kind of diffused
uh and almost verges on a kind of
nihilism if you really want to look at
that so it's like if the if the value is
identical with the global dynamical
properties of the organism well that
identity relationship doesn't allow it
to have any function in its own right
you know you could just describe the
whole system purely in terms of its
Dynamics
um and so it's kind of like a slippery
Road what they want to do is shift the
notion of value
to the level of the agent so as a whole
the agent uh you know has an intrinsic
perspective on the world that means that
value shouldn't be for some
sub-component inside the Asian that's
the kind of motivation of why why you
don't want to go with the kind of
classical View
but then the new view where you bring in
this agent level perspective with an
intrinsic concern for its own
supervisation and about the world
um what's the scientific account of that
well you've removed value now from the
sub-personal story and put it in the
personal level but you haven't given us
an account of how the person on the sub
person will actually connect with each
other all right and so so basically
you've actually just like voided the
kind of sub-personal level of any kind
of relevance in terms of
connecting with something on the Asian
level so
yeah so so I think we're on the same
page so like yeah one way of thinking
about eruption theory is to say uh we
need to do more here that you know if we
are wanting to make a place for value at
the personal level such that we can say
you know I am talking with you because I
want to right there's an agent level
kind of characterization of what's going
on then we still have to tell a story
about how that Asian level wanting
something actually connects with all the
material basis of our Behavior such that
it realizes that intention and that's
something that hasn't been done uh you
know there's like these are two
different levels of description and yeah
there's no representations and no values
at the level of the empirical story at
the material basis and everything
happens at the level of filmology
um but yeah there's a disconnect between
these two stories so far
yes and it's not the same thing as the
hard problem or the question of
awareness it's a causal relevance and
the image that came to mind is like a
buoy in the ocean and we explain its uh
Movement by appealing to the flow of the
waves and then uh making a model in
which a sophisticated buoy also going
with the flow is able to navigate and
surf or something
you've explained away Surfing by a
really delicately balanced set of
channels such that the flow is one of
the same as surfing in that context but
that gives no causal relevance to
wanting to surf and so one is either
left with this just a happening view of
wanting exactly or
to just say no it never mattered yeah so
your your example is quite close
actually to the kind of original
materana example of structural coupling
uh where he
treats people or organisms more
generally
as a boat drifting on the sea that's
being pushed by the waves and the winds
and so the direction of the boat is not
directly determined by the wind hitting
it
um you know imagine a sailing board
right so the Sails are up the wind's
pushing it but instead of going in the
direction of the wind what it does is go
sideways right and so that's his example
of saying structure determinism which
means there's a certain kind of autonomy
of the system with respect to what
impinges on it from the environment
um but you know that's one thing but the
other thing is to say that there's
absolutely nothing happening there at
the level of intentions of wanting to go
that way or that way or that there is a
function of wanting to sail in the first
place and things like that there's no
room for that in that story
um you know we are all like like you
know uh just drifting so to speak and
that's this concept of neutral uh drift
that they put forward so um yeah so
we're we're basically yeah so this is
like the you know the kind of conundrum
that is faced by this kind of biological
biology of cognition and active approach
but I mean also of employee cognition
more generally
um so the question is how we can do
something different there
um let me see maybe just to unpack a
little bit more of the the inactive
approach with this diagram this is the
kind of uh because we're bringing in
biology of cognition just now and auto
courses so maybe it's good to just say a
few words about how the electrical push
differs a little bit from those previous
Traditions
um and so the classical view of Auto
Grace is by Mata Rana and varila is
about cell production
um so that means there's a system that
creates itself and its own identity
where identity is the defining
organization of that system and that's
coupled with this environment and that's
all and that's it and so as long as you
don't die you're just gonna persist
coupling and self-producing uh and if
you die well that's it um and so just
because of that there will be a negative
selection that if you're not
particularly well coupled with your
environment you're not adapted you will
not persist and so that's the whole
story of biology recognition there's no
level of value or intentions or agency
or experience these are all kind of
narrative redescriptions but that don't
have any kind of cause of relevance for
understanding the real behavior of these
systems
and so enter the inactive approach and
they say no we need to bring an
intrinsic goals and concern perspectives
and
um and this has to do with the finitude
of the organism and the precariousness
and and so on
um and then for a long time it started
feeling like uh we're kind of like
starting to create like a shopping list
of properties again like you know it has
to be self-producing it has to be
adaptive it has to be precarious right
and that's exactly the kind of thing
that uh Alto quizzes didn't want to do
he wanted to do a kind of first
principle operational definition of life
rather than this classic shopping list
of what it's like where you basically
list your favorite properties of living
systems and then say you know if a
system more or less satisfies most of
these properties I'm going to call it
living right so it started going again
into that direction and then there was
this nice work by the Apollo and called
it in recent years where they tied Auto
places a little bit more closely with
the thermodynamics of it and that meant
that
you think about what Auto places needs
to do in a material context on the one
hand of course it needs to maintain its
kind of structural Integrity so it needs
to be closed off somehow from the
environment in order to be able to
regulate its interaction with the
environment but he can't be completely
closed off because if that was the case
it would just like starve itself to
death you know it needs energy to do the
work but that energy comes from the
environment right so actually it does it
needs to be open to energy Flows In
order to be able to do the work that
needs to be
Integrity maintaining so there's
suddenly two conflicting needs here on
the one hand it needs to close itself
off as much as possible that would mean
it would be as autonomous as possible
and yet at the same time to maximize the
energy it has to do its work it would
actually have to be as open as possible
to these flows which would undermine its
Integrity so the life is faced with this
weird primordial tension of having to
satisfied two needs that can never be
satisfied fully and never at the same
time and so then the key move is to say
that this is the reason why life is
precarious intrinsically it can never be
in a stable situation and the only thing
it can do is regulate album open or how
close it is over time and that this
regulation then becomes the basis for
agency that's why life is different from
other kinds of far from equilibrium
systems
this this reminds me by analogy to
attention-based learning where just
um dilating and paying more attention or
constricting and paying less attention
is uh able to be part of an Adaptive
strategy for dealing with streams of
incoming noisy or partial information
and maybe one reason why
um attention feels so tied up
with agency and so precarious as well
because it's it's
um walking that impossible tightrope and
it knows it can't be on either Extreme
as you pointed out they both result
pretty rapidly in death so we're only
going to come to see organisms that do
have a dynamical navigation of this
tension
yeah yeah so actually this is a general
principle I think that you know this is
the the origin of it or maybe like the
the most basic form of it but I think
it's true of everything to some extent
every time there is a way in which we're
coupling with the environment there will
always be a tension between doing things
your way and actually at the same time
having to be open to the environment
um and like another kind of area that's
interesting in this regard because we're
doing EG hyper scanning in our lab is
that most of the time when people think
about hyperscanning they think just
about the coupling so the question is
how much interpersonal neural synchrony
for example is there in the condition
but what they don't think about is that
actually you know that probably what's
happening is that sometimes we are more
strongly coupled and sometimes we are
more you know distant disengage more
coupled disengage couple disengage if we
were always super coupled that would be
kind of pathological I think you know it
would be very hard to maintain that and
it would feel very uncomfortable and you
wouldn't get anything done so so
actually a sensitivity to this kind of
tension actually has methodological
implications down the line because we
still don't have to ask questions about
the diacronic changes in the strength of
coupling of the organism with this
environment and if you ignore that and
just take the average let's say we might
actually completely miss the phenomena
what other just analogy there is with
so-called futile Cycles in Biochemistry
where you'll have like the forward and
the reverse reaction happening at the
same time and people sometimes
characterize that as wasteful yet when
you pull back it's actually the the
coexistence of these two Pathways that
allows adaptivity and so it's like the
paradigm shift is not to see it as
wasteful but adaptive it's just simply
adaptive it's simply valuable for the
cell to participate in that um
bi-directional activity
right yeah and just another example
sleep all right so in our culture sleep
is not really valued right you know
energy drinks are a huge industry you
know it feels like if we could engineer
sleep out of people then you know people
would go for this and you know I would
make a lot of money with that but the
question is you know given that sleep is
a really vulnerable state for the
organism and we find it across all
animals to some extent uh it must have
really important reasons that it wasn't
selected against right so even though
probably the majority of animals die
when they're sleeping let's say right
because they they don't they aren't
aware of dangerous and predators and so
on still we're sleeping you know for a
large chunk of each day
why right uh and so it's this thing like
you know you need sometimes you need to
decouple and if you don't decouple
you're just going to dissolve basically
you know think about sleep deprivation
you know if you do too much you actually
physically die of sleep deprivation so
it's not just you know you know down
time so to speak it's absolutely
essential for proper functioning and so
just bringing it back to the paper one
way of thinking about what's going on
here is that it's not just that we are
opening and closing uh you can ask like
why if it's not a metabolic reason what
could be the reason for this
um and we've got a companion paper for
this one that's gonna come out and buy a
systems hopefully soon where we have a
little model that shows that if you push
a system far from equilibrium make it an
open system basically and then close it
again let it fall into its equilibrium
State and then repeat that over time and
at the same time you add a little bit of
historicity in the background which is
the kind of sedimentation of the states
it has visited in the past such that
it's more likely to return to states
that has visited in the past what
happens is that the system starts
building up an associative memory of the
Stables forms it has visited in the past
and can actually then start generalizing
two forms of stability that has never
accounted in the past and that if you
didn't have this kind of setup would
never in principle encounter because
it's just too hard to find in the state
space and so we basically redoing here
the kind of agency diagram that I just
explained and we're just making explicit
the historical dimension of this process
is that if you're switching between far
from equilibrium and equilibrium modes
and there's a little bit of historicity
here that's really when agency emerges
because the system then becomes able to
jump to new configurations that would
have been otherwise practically
impossible to reach for it
so for me that's another another story
so you don't you don't need eruptions to
to think about this but it kind of fits
into the same
um you know larger rethinking about the
you know what's the role possibly of of
breaks actually and that's all like
that's that's the bigger picture I think
we should you know allow much more room
for
irrationality uh indeterminism noise uh
you know when things don't work the way
they should and just say that that's a
necessary compliment for things going
well I think that's if that could be
like one of the take-home messages of
our conversation yeah and that reminds
me actually of a lot of empirical work
on heart rate variability uh gait gate
variability and um one Viewpoint the car
Viewpoint would be well you want those
uh steps to be really even length you
want the heartbeat to be like a
metronome you want the breathing to be
like a metronome but in fact it's the
opposite that are associated with all
cause
um mortality such that higher
variability patterns are associated with
um more vital Health that's right yeah
yeah
um and uh I mean there are good reasons
for that right so there's this whole
control theory aspect to it that we want
the controller to have higher degrees of
freedom than that which is controlled
and so you know at heart rate
variability is important because you
want to keep your blood pressure
constant no matter what kind of
situations you put yourself into so
basically the heart has to take up all
the the slack so to speak of the
variable conditions of me getting up
from the chair and so on and the blood
pressure has to stay constant right so
that's why you have a lot of variability
there
um but there's the more General notion
of thinking about why is variability
associated with health and then maybe
eruption Theory comes in again a little
bit in that as we will see because it's
basically giving Arguments for saying
that signs of agency making a difference
might look like increased variability in
the system
so to get there let me just start to get
a bit more narrow and what is the
eruption Theory trying to achieve
and so and the next section of this
paper
um uh what I'm trying to propose is that
the challenge that is lying ahead of us
is thinking of developing a motivation
involving account of motivated activity
so that the reason why I put it like
this is that
um I think the large majority of work on
motivated activity and again remember
I'm I'm using motivated activity as an
umbrella term
or Asian level Concepts such as
intentions beliefs desires experiences
you know goals
um you know so and you pick your
favorite let's say intentions right or
Consciousness for that matter
um that you want to say that
Consciousness makes a difference for
what you're doing are your intentions
well what what are the standard ways of
accounting for that
um you know we can say that in terms of
Consciousness you know maybe we can go
with Walter Freeman's approach which was
quite influential for the early work of
Barilla and Thompson on neurophonology
and Freeman says well Consciousness
um you know we've got this order
parameter in the brain uh which kind of
like organizes the you know the firing
activity of all the neurons and so given
that that's a high level property
immersion property that has Downstream
effects and we think that Consciousness
is a kind of Asian level property that
has Downstream effects so why don't we
say that Consciousness works on the
brain through the order parameter
okay so so uh uh that's you know let's
say that's one possibility right let's
think about intentions
we can think about intentions again in
terms of dynamical sincere many people
worked on it uh Juarez has a book on it
uh Deacon worked on it
um there's a whole literature and
philosophy of of action that applies a
kind of dynamical approach to saying
well what what intentions do is uh they
Place constraints
on the degrees of freedom of system such
that it realizes the action that is you
know needs to take place
um and so it's basically emerging
constraints that have top-down effects
on your degrees of freedom so kind of
similar to the order parameter idea
um uh but my main issue with these kinds
of accounts and there are more of them
is that they kind of offload or
Outsource the efficacy of the higher
level property to something else
because I could also just tell the same
story let's say of the order parameter
without talking about Consciousness at
all I can say look the you know I'm
going to be a complete reductivist
physicalist and I want to understand how
the brain works I could still tell the
story of hey there's all these neurons
interacting there's an emerging process
that has top-down constraints and how
the neurons are firing
nothing there commits me to saying
anything about intentions or
Consciousness so then what's the point
like why do we need to appeal to
Consciousness in the first place we
don't get any explanatory Advantage you
know the the neuroscientific story
doesn't get any extra advantage and also
if you wanted to explain something about
how Consciousness work well you're also
not saying anything because you know it
makes no difference to the other story
and so that's the kind of situation that
we're in so that when I say I want a
motivation involving account I want
something where the motivation itself as
such as a motivation
makes a difference to the system and not
just because I'm identifying it with
something else like an order parameter
or constraint right so I think if we
don't have this ambition then we're
basically missing the point I mean this
is gonna this is really the kind of main
challenge that I see facing us right and
so eruption theory is one attempt at
solving this problem
and in more recent work I'm gonna kind
of try to you know crystallize this out
as the hard problem of efficacy how do
we make sure that our Asian level
properties that we care about actually
our thickestness in the world and not
just because they're super being on or
identical with or whatever you want to
say with properties that are not
actually at the Asian level
that's that's to my mind you know that's
that's where this work is situated and
if you can't solve that I think it's a
huge failure uh I mean we all assume
that our intentions matter and that our
beliefs matter and that our desires
matter and that they make a difference
for how we behave but so far all our
best scientific accounts don't allow
this
they pop out at the last moment and say
actually all the real causal work is
being done by other things right and so
so there's always this like danger in
the background saying that actually all
of our mental life is epiphenomenal all
of Consciousness is every phenomenal
that that's always there like somewhere
lingering in the background and this is
where this debate has been stalling for
decades so I really just want to like
say let's bite the bullet and say you
know we need to try something different
and maybe it won't work
um but you know if you don't even try if
you don't even see that there's a
problem here uh you know that that's
that's uh you know I think at the moment
it's unacceptable right we really need
to try to do something different here
all right so the the two short thoughts
there
um if we don't intend for intention to
be a difference that makes a difference
all our intentions are on the table and
they're all for naught and then the um
the second thought is uh the causal
efficacy of the map is not causal
efficacy in the territory so just saying
that a causal parameter in an equation
has an influence on another parameter or
an equation isn't what one set out to do
unless they were doing like forensic
equation analysis
right right yeah so so I think people
get lost
um
in the sense that you can do a lot of
scientific work in the old Paradigm
right you can happily study
Consciousness all you want and say hey
I'm Gonna Leave This problem to the
other people this is the neuroscientist
and the neuroscientists are happily
studying how Topline constraints affect
all the neuralifying and you know they
leave the problem of conscious and
intentions to the psychologist and
everybody happily publishes a lot of
papers and hopes that somewhere along
the line these things will meet together
um but yeah unfortunately uh you know
just saying that there is a kind of
mapping
is not the answer to this problem of
efficacy so just bring it kind of like
very clearly let's say
um an example that everybody familiar is
like a grandmother neuron or Jennifer
Aniston neuron or a grid cell neuron or
whatever right so we can make a
correlational analysis and say the
firing of this neuron correlates with
you know the person person perceiving
this image on the screen let's say or
being in this part of the maze or
whatever
um and that's great uh that's that's
very exciting right that we can do that
kind of work but then the question
becomes well how is that content
representational content or Association
making a difference for how that neuron
is firing
and then well what are we going to say
there I mean like we can look at that
neuron all we want we can study it and
it's you know down to the nanoscale if
you want and there's never going to be
any place where you can say oh now I
understand how Jennifer Aniston makes a
difference to this neuron
and like it's just not going to happen
you're going to have you know chemistry
you're going to have electrical
potentials you're going to have fluxes
you're gonna have membranes you're gonna
you know all this messy stuff that you
know the the neurobiologists look at but
you're not going to have a point where
you say oh I see the desire here or I
see the value here
um and so to just say that these neurons
represent a location in a maze
has absolutely no efficacy at the level
of describing how that neuron behaves
and again as long as we don't even see
this as a problem I think we are lost
because we know we can publish all the
papers we want and say hey this part of
the brain correlates with this and so on
um but the fact that it has content
mental content associated with it
doesn't appear ultimately in the
scientific account of how the systems
behave at some point it disappears at a
higher level it's there we can say
looking from outside the system we can
look at what's happening in the
environment we can ask the subject and
we can look inside the brain and we see
all these links very nicely all right
Learners forget about these links let's
go deeper into the brain and like look
at all these you know Cellular Systems
and so on oh but what happened to all
this other stuff right at some point
you're just magically vanished and you
know it's a kind of Disappearing trick
because we don't even ask the question
how did all this extra knowledge that we
were positing at the higher level make a
difference to what the neuron is doing
here all we've got is electrical
potentials let's say
um yeah and so that's the current state
of the art where we don't even see that
there's a problem here that there's a
gap here
um and so uh some colleagues hooked on
mine call this the hard problem of
content like you know how is it even
possible to say that there is content
associated with this kind of neuron uh
you know which could be true or false
could be correct or wrong could be you
know different levels of accuracy and so
on so all these normative conditions are
completely missing from the picture of
how the neuron works and so what I'm
trying to say here there's an additional
problem which is that even if we could
give an account of how it is that these
neurons also have mental properties like
pairing mental content there's an
additional problem to say how could that
content make a difference to how those
neurons behave right now we're talking
about the neural level but it's the same
kind of issue again like how do we move
from something that's normative to
something that makes a difference uh you
know empirically speaking in the
material basis of it so yeah
um again deep deep issues uh and the
eruption theory is just like a small
stab in that direction but I hope that
uh what it can do at least is get people
thinking uh that you know there's a
really interesting problem here that
we've been blind to and we should pay
attention to
so let's get into eruptions Theory then
um and it has a couple of of axioms uh
that
um I think the idea of this so these
axioms are supposed to be uh General and
intuitive enough that hopefully
everybody can agree with them okay so if
you don't agree with them let me know
because these are not supposed to be
controversial okay everybody should be
just saying yep okay I can sign off on
this so Axiom number one the
motivational efficacy and agents
motivations as such make a difference to
the material basis of the agent's
Behavior okay so that's like I want to
make a point by lifting my finger okay
my finger just went up great you know
that it's as trivial as that I'm just
saying that you know whatever intentions
we have we can see that it has material
consequences in the world
this is his everyday experience our
whole life world is based on this that's
him right we didn't believe in this you
know it was like the whole all of social
order would collapse somehow I mean we
just assume that there's a relationship
between people's motivations and
intentions and how they behave all right
so that's Axiom one
Axiom 2 brings out the problem here
which is that it has intention with our
best science so far
so action 2 says incomplete materiality
it is impossible to measure the
scientific instruments how motivations
as such make a difference to the
material basis of behavior and so this
is what we've been talking about you
know no matter how close I study how the
brain or the body works and you know put
it under the microscope put it under uh
whatever the scalpel open up your head
look inside you know your brain whatever
we never see motivations as such making
a difference to what anything behaving
it's just material processes
so for most people this is where the
real problems this is the problem of
free will this is the Mind Body problem
this is the problem of mental causation
you know this is the problem of you know
can there be the cause of closure of
Nature and like how does the Mind fit
into the natural order all of that is
impact you know in these two axioms
which each of them I think we should
accept so I'm not saying we should
reject them what I'm saying is that we
should live with this tension and not
try to immediately jump to a conclusion
that would remove it both of these
axioms are independently valid now the
question is how do we deal with the
tension between them and so a first step
in that direction
is to introduce another Axiom
right so action number three under
determined materiality an agent's
behavior is underdetermined by its
material basis and this is crucial this
comes out of the the discussion we had
in the beginning that from a dynamical
systems point of view
everything is predetermined
by the laws of the Dynamics and the
initial conditions no surprises right so
I could always rewind the tape and know
exactly what's going to happen
uh and that's to some extent the kind of
the concept of nature that a lot of
inactive but also cognitive science in
general uh works with it's like we're
asking these hard questions about how to
fit Axiom one and two together in the
context of trying to fit it into a
Clockwork universe that you know was in
fashion at the time of let's say Newton
and LaPlace but it's long gone and the
rest of the Natural Sciences right so
why are we forcing ourselves to try to
solve these ultimate problems
in the context of a physics that's you
know century is outdated you know that
that doesn't make much sense to me so I
think this Axiom here might be
questionable for some people who really
think that
um you know science should be in the
business of recovering a deterministic
worldview and so in for them even
quantum physics is not an argument
against it because they believe that
some future development of quantum
physics will show that everything is
deterministic after all like a kind of
Einstein's you know goes down and play
dice kind of view
um but I think that you know why why
should we want that uh you know it it
feels much more natural to say that
nature is messy uh uh and like you know
there's degrees of freedom that can't be
always closed and so on so again this
this actually might be the most
controversial of the three but I think
in terms of our best science it's
actually relatively consistent with what
we know about nature there are aspects
of nature in which we cannot with
absolute Precision predetermine what
will happen next even if we knew
everything about the universe at that
moment and in this past
um and so
all right that's for all of nature that
doesn't say anything specific about us
and how we interact with the world but
that's just to say that the only reason
why Axiom 2 looks like its intention
with axiom1 is if you assume that Axiom
2 also gives you a complete account of
nature
right if it gave you a complete account
of nature there will be no room for
action one
if Axiom 2 that we don't find Direct
measurable evidence of motivation making
difference all right but at the same
time we know that action 2 also doesn't
give us the full picture of what's going
on all right then the tension is
slightly diffused because there's space
for something to make a difference which
is not accounted for in Axiom 2. all
right so it's kind of just like opening
the window of possibilities just
logically speaking for the moment
all right so those are the the three
axioms
um
now let's see what does eruption Theory
make of this
um so
they kind of breakthrough conceptual
breakthrough that that occurred to me in
terms of getting serious about how
something like an Asian level property
could make a difference in the material
basis that is described by Axiom II
while not violating accept two which
means that my motivation involving
account can't just say hey there are
motivations inside your brain okay that
would be this kind of going back to the
diagram maybe that we had in the
beginning where there's a value system
inside the system somewhere making
judgments right so that's kind of like
placing the value inside the organism
but it can also not just be an emerging
property like an order parameter which
was kind of like the the right hand side
of that diagram where value is this kind
of emergent uh property neither of those
works for me neither of them gives me a
motivation involving account basically
they substitute motivations for
something else whether it's a local or
Global property of the system
so what would a motivation making a
difference in the material basis
actually look like
can't appear as a motivation because
it's not I mean it's it's not it's not
possible to ask the question of nature
by measuring it and then say no the
answer is not three it's a motivation it
just doesn't work like that right and so
what how can it appear well it must
appear somehow as part of the material
basis but it's going to be a very
strange kind of object because it's not
really an object because it's normative
because it's qualitative and so what I
want to do is flip this on this head
like what uh the motivation does is
underdetermine the material constraints
it basically means that let's imagine
that I'm recording from your brain and I
got like you know my time series a
signal
um you know recording
and all the kind of material
organizational properties of your body
and the environment are all constraining
how you know your electrical potential
is changing over time
now if I wanted to say that something is
happening in your signal here which is
because of a motivation making a
difference to how you behave
well that motivation cannot be captured
by the material organizational
constraints directly it's something else
making a difference and something else
making a difference from the point of
view of the material organizational
properties of the system will look like
noise
it will look like something breaks in
the system that's unpredictable
something that is unintelligible like no
matter how much I study the system no
matter how much I describe it understand
it something just happened in my
measurement that I cannot fully account
for no matter what Precision I have no
matter how much I know about the history
of my recordings and that's because it's
the motivation itself that's making a
difference and it cannot be captured at
that level of description
and so
um the way I put it here as a working
hypothesis is that the more an agents
and body activity is motivated
the less that activity is determined by
its material basis right because other
things are shaping the activity and they
are not identifiable with the material
basis because they're motivations
because their desires because their
beliefs because they are wants
um and so although all of those have a
material basis they are not identical
with that material basis they make a
difference but that difference cannot be
reduced to a difference just at the
level of a material basis
and this might sound a little bit
strange but uh to some extent
um it fits quite well with certain
Trends in the inactive approach to link
the philosophy that it does with Eastern
style of thinking so in Japan for
example we have a a school of Zen which
has a nice phrase which was very popular
for virula for example that says if you
think about the relationship between the
mind and the body
um well it's not one
okay so you can't just collapse them
but it's also not two
you know so a complete Independence
the right way of thinking about the
relationship between the mind and the
body is that it's not one and not two
right and that's it that's all they have
to say it's not one and it's not two and
so it's it's a kind of strange
intermediate thing
um and that means that there are trust
order effects their interaction effects
one can make a difference to the other
but without collapsing into the other
um and so to recognize when this happens
when does the one side reach into the
other and make a difference without
becoming the other side
that difference will look unintelligible
from within that side is something they
cannot grasp on its own terms because
it's coming from somewhere else with a
different kind of specific qualities in
terms of its ontology
and I mean this is all very abstract but
like you know uh when we go concretely
now
um it leads itself quite nicely to
quantification because we do have
measures of surprise we do have measures
of unpredictability we do have measures
of noise in the system
um and so
um the the way in which I propose to as
an approximation to to measure eruptions
is just through entropy right what they
do what is happening is that your
motivation is causing a certain kind of
disorder in the system disorder in the
sense that purely material
organizational constraints are bracketed
for a moment
which is the same as saying that they're
having less of an ordering influence on
the system
so it's a disorder if you can measure
the entropy
now in the classical libertarian work on
this you know once you get rid of
determinism there's always this danger
of like well doesn't that mean that
everything is now random like how would
that be useful right
um but you know from the point of view
of complex adapter systems that's not a
a worry anymore because actually we've
got lots of interesting work that shows
that
um breaks you know going back to Ashby
actually the source of adaptivity you
know that they're what allows the system
to be flexible uh and to to adapt to its
environment that's what is exactly what
is needed in order to be flexible
and so far from saying that what you
said in the beginning like uh earlier
that variability is actually a sign of
Health right so at to some extent you
know it's not bad that the way in which
our motivations make a difference to our
body is by destabilization by
disordering by bracketing constraints
that's exactly the kind of degrees of
freedom that our bodies need in order to
be flexible and healthy so it's a very
nice fit with what we already know
actually we know that these are markers
of consciousness of agency of Health but
now what we have is a kind of larger
framework that explains why is it the
case that let's say neural entropy
tracks levels of awareness
oh that's great right no not not it fits
very nicely now we can it's not just no
longer empirical work that says well you
know we're measuring this and we're
correlating how much entropy with
whether you're asleep or comatose or in
a psychedelic state but actually we can
say well you know giving our a priori
principles the axioms that I outline we
expect that when these things affect
each other given that the axioms cannot
be violated this will Express itself as
a certain kind of perturbation or
disorder appearing in our measurements
and that's what we find
and so now we have a really nice
theoretical framework that can actually
explain to us why our variability and
entropy associated with agency and with
health
and so yes we'll try to do a little
restatement and and see if I'm on the
right track here so I'm
um
imagining a person in a device that can
move their arm
so in one situation where this device
entirely moves their arm for them
100 of the variance in movement is
explained by external observables and so
whether now they may have not had a
motivation to move it or maybe they
really did but if that would be um Epi
phenomenal because it basically didn't
make a difference the work was all done
by the external apparatus
um so we can say 100 of the variance was
explained
what is every single situation other
than that well it's less than a hundred
percent of the variance explained so
there's some difference there's some you
know r squared that's between zero and
one and in all like real living and
breathing situations it's a lot less
than one so there's some space
where
um the uh material basis
even if we believe that we're fully
measured wouldn't fully explain it
exactly the second piece that I see
happening is motivation at least in in
our lives at least in my to-do list it
feels like an ordering principle and and
there's like a way or there's a sense
that it is an ordering principle but
especially in connection with Ashby and
the brakes
motivation could be an Adaptive
disordering principle that actually
supports the movement to Adaptive regime
order exactly yeah so it locally
disorganizes but then at some meso scale
or perhaps some some macro scale it
provides an ordering and
um as per that first apparatus thought
experiment
the extent to which motivation is
disordering
um the space it has to play is in the
Unexplained variance by the material
consequences that's exactly right yeah
yep you got it so let me just unpack
that a little bit more so good that you
you prompt me
um you're right so we are not anymore on
this view directly in control of our
behavior and that's a little bit
disconcerting at first to to Grapple
like what we can do to our bodies is set
the conditions we can open spaces or uh
we can open degrees of freedom we can
open spaces of potentiality but we have
to trust our bodies and their
environments to fill those spaces in the
right way
all right so it's like I'm opening a
space and say voila right now is the
possibility for a new Behavior to emerge
or to behavior to switch to something
else but what behavior is going to be
selected that's not directly under our
control that will depend on our history
our predisposition our body capacities
our body memory it will depend on the
affordances of the environment what kind
of interaction process are we engaged in
and so suddenly all of this work and
embody cognition fits in very neatly all
of that suddenly comes into play and
says actually action self-organizes uh
based on all of these criteria of
historicity and then body man and
situatedness what we do as agents is
open spaces for those processes to take
place
and that's our agency and then of course
we kind of upload the rest to our bodies
and as long as everything goes well our
bodies are actually quite capable of
responding in the right way but that's
something that's acquired that's not
something that's pre-given so to speak
we need to undergo the right history to
acquire these dispositions and these
Tendencies such that when we're in a
situation and we open the space the
space is filled in the right way and
that's very interesting this kind of
like it's got a mixed concept of agency
that we're partially in control but like
just the last bit excludes our graphs we
can't force it
um but I feel actually that to some
extent that's kind of what experience
feels like like I can I can try to make
this point by speaking and then I kind
of find the words most of the time but I
just have to trust my body that the
right words come out I cannot choose the
words in advance and the same is true of
all of our actions like you know I can
make an intention to reach something but
sometimes I misreach you know and for
some people who have a body that's not
quite optimally organize reaching can be
a big problem actually right so so we
really are kind of dependent on the body
to fill these spaces in the right way
and affordances are a big part of this
too so
um you know there's a general idea that
we should choose our environments
carefully right because they will shape
the way we behave and think and so on
and yeah it fits again perfectly with
this story that
um we open the spaces but then the
environment will solicit certain kinds
of propensities from us and we're not
always fully in control of exactly what
it is that will come out of us
um and um so it's a kind of compromise
between a kind of libertarian point of
view a full control over our behavior
and a kind of deterministic point of
view of completely lack of control of
what's Happening where yeah we can
decide to open a space of possibilities
but actually it's other forces that
close the space
awesome please continue many many
interesting angles yeah I mean uh that
part I skipped it but good that you
brought up um is described also in the
in the paper in terms of a thesis of
Attunement
so it kind of goes with this that uh
um I have three thesis here one is the
eruption thesis which says that if they
are cross-border effects we will see
them as a disordering consequence in the
domain that's being affected
um because it's coming from outside of
that domain
and then if that's the case we have this
challenge in front of us how do we
explain that this this order actually
does some good work for the organism uh
and one thing there is that there are
two possibilities of this order one is
that it could be a whole system
consequence so you know there's a lot of
work looking at Silver inferentiality uh
and Barilla himself tried to link also
quizzes with girdle's work on the
incompleteness theorem and so on and so
maybe actually eruptions are system
level consequences of self-reference and
incompleteness at that level but you
know that's further work or it's
something that happens very locally that
you know at the smallest micro scale
there's a kind of glitch in the system
and then permits kind of like a
disordering of some you know particle
configurations or something like that
basically
um you know using up some energy there
uh that's also possible if that's the
case we would have to have a scaling up
effect so how do we go from a small
disorder that is barely even measurable
or maybe not even measurable because
almost almost infinitely small
perturbation to something that makes a
difference at the level of the scale of
behavior right but again we've got a
whole nice body of work in artificial
life to slot in there which is that and
the organisms are organized so to be
sensitive to very small differences
right so this is a self-organized
criticality we can talk about chaos we
can talk about scale free Dynamics so
there's a whole body of work that
already shows us that the body is
organized so as to macro to amplify very
small perturbations that's nice now we
again we have an interesting idea of
like why is it the case that the body is
organized in that way in this kind of
poised way and then if you do have
eruption scaled up to the macroscopic
level still there would be the sense of
like you know that that's not useful
really to have a huge disorder washing
through your body
unless you're doing it in the context of
being attuned already to the environment
in the right way in which case actually
it will become a source of flexibility
such that you're no longer trapped into
kind of committed coping like you know
uh um you know I have to continue like
highly ears Hammer right I have to
hammer I have to hammer like you know my
house is burning down but I have to
hammer I have to hammer like you know it
would be very bad if we are really good
at doing a single task and could never
switch to another task and so how how
open are we to switching tasks
um that openness the switching task can
be regulated by the eruptions of the
microscopic level but like I said like
exactly what action will happen next
will depend on how we are attuned to the
situation
and so this achievement then brings in
this whole working in body cognition of
how a lot of our action selection
happens in the uh organism environment
interaction process
um
it makes me think about Reservoir
Computing and about the the environment
as a dampener for the eruption because
if if we do grant that there is
endogenous
excitation so it's not just an outside
in the car the computer world so we we
are going to a grant that there's some
kind of endogenous generativity
um or spontaneity then when it
interfaces with the environment there's
basically two options from a dynamical
systems perspective either the
environment could dampen the excitation
like you could yell and then that could
dampen or it would be a positive
um feedback and it would be like a
spiraling out of control at which point
that coupling wouldn't um would
basically escalate until it reached some
other negative feedback point so the
environment plays a a critical dampening
role through Attunement so so that the
um so that that
um
break can find a new non-equilibrium
steady state or A New Path right so
there's a kind of question here of how
what's the right balance for how much
eruptions do you need in order to you
know be an optimal
situation so as you said like there
could be situations when it happens too
much right that you don't ever have time
to properly settle into a new attractor
or into a new activity
um and maybe we could think of some
disorders like schizophrenia in this way
right there's so much you know the same
motivational involvement and what's
going on all the time hyperreflexivity
that you're basically destabilizing you
know the system constantly and never
allowing it to properly settle and
there's interesting links there also
with the fact that there you know
there's their body memory gets lost you
know like uh and so on so
um there's that it can go to in too much
Direction and also there's the other
direction that says what if it doesn't
happen enough you know a certain kind of
rigidity will set in you know you will
not be able to switch context easily you
will not be able to deal with novelty
easily
um you know and maybe something like
depression could be something in that
direction that you know like you feel
like the world's closed off to you
there's no longer any possibilities for
change or development
um and that brings then like you know
this this whole work into another
Direction which is can we use it to
better understand how to treat people
um you know so what if that the
schizophrenic what can we do for them to
kind of like dampen more maybe the
eruptions that they're constantly
sending into their body versus for the
depressed patient maybe it's the
opposite how can we make them more
susceptible to being open to eruptions
and interestingly it can be both ways
right so maybe in the case of depression
it's something that's happening at the
level of the person level the Asian
level experience level
at the middle of motivations and the
body itself might actually be fine to
some extent that's an interesting
possibility here right and then in that
case we have to work on the level of
their experience how do we get them more
motivated to some extent and then that
will kind of kick-start things or on the
other hand it could be a physiological
thing right you know the at the person
level everything is fine except that the
brain maybe for example in Alzheimer's
and Dementia is crossed it over and it's
no longer susceptible to these degrees
of freedom being injected into it right
and so what looked from the outside as
two cases of becoming maybe more rigid
and less responsive and less flexible
might have opposite sources in terms of
does the disorder lie more at the the
call side of the eruptions or the
consequence side of their options right
and so we can think about you know this
now because previously these things were
collapsed right we couldn't easily
differentiate them but now we have these
two possibilities to look at this like
um and a lot of the interventions that
do work in the clinic they say for
depression for for example kind of feel
like they're almost like simulating
eruptions right so why does psychedelics
work so well for for depression well
because it's a huge destabilization of
the system right and it works both at
the motivational level that you have a
huge increase in the degrees of your
cognitive processes of your experiential
processes which then also you know like
destabilizes the system at the brain
level
um or another example uh obsessive
compulsive disorder uh and you know why
does something like deep brain
stimulation help
um or electric convulsive therapy in
other cases like you know for
schizophrenia why is it that these
seemingly kind of crude interventions of
just injecting a lot of arbitrary noise
into the brain which is irrelevant from
the point of view of what the brain
itself is doing right so it's undergoing
its processes and suddenly from the
outside we inject you know like these
hard uh you know activity that doesn't
is not contextualized it doesn't fit in
with what the brain was already doing
and yet what happens is that it actually
makes people feel better it makes them
feel refreshed it makes them feel more
stable it makes them feel more flexible
why why should the injection of these
kind of like breaks of activity have
these consequences and so with a Russian
Theory we can actually start to
conceptualize this in a different way
and think that you know what we're doing
there is maybe amplifying or
substituting you know uh eruptions
artificially uh and and the body is
there being responsive to them and then
once things are like more you know let's
say well oiled again the person
themselves can like you know take over
the role again of of you know doing
eruptions themselves rather than having
it induced from from the outside
and it makes me think of the kind of
unreasonable efficacy of just general
physiological interventions like sleep
walking eating cold showers meditation
like why does it all why do all roads
kind of Channel back to these
large-scale breaks because they
um at a a deeper nested level
allow the adaptivity to exercise
especially the exercise one you know
there's a recent paper and and been
asked about you know measuring neural
entropy in a huge fmri data set and then
ranking like what's the highest level
and actually motion-based tasks have the
highest level of neural entropy
associated with it and you know for
people doing EEG you know we kind of
know it because you know it's a nuisance
right you say how can I do my EG and I
have to like keep people sitting and not
moving because if they start moving my
signals go over the place and you know
that a lot of that is muscle artifacts
but you know in general the idea is
clear right like the more you you move
the more things are happening uh in in
your brain and so
um yeah just going for a walk uh you
know actually uh could could really make
some differences
yes many I mean this is the heart of um
of the inactive Quest and of active
inference which is if we only wanted to
describe the special case of active
inference where
um there was no action or where actions
were being caused by something that
didn't matter then it would collapse
back onto passive inference but the
challenge of scientific analysis of
behavior
is actually
um
uh serious and I think that you're
pointing to some uh kind of figure and
ground type conceptualizations such that
what has been thrown into the variance
unexplained category
um the motivation was getting thrown out
with the bathwater that's right yeah
that's a very nice way of putting it and
um maybe just a final thought here and
that has to do with the replication
crisis you know something just to ponder
right like why is it that in Psychology
it's so hard for people to behave the
same way and experiments you know and
and we try to counteract that by having
larger sample sizes and more control
conditions and so on and you know if you
can't replicate you we we think that you
know I guess it wasn't controlled
properly or we didn't have enough sample
size and so on but what if all that
variability is just actually a positive
signal that someone you know took the
task seriously and made a difference to
what's going on and and people are not
like machines like you know we can't
control directly how we will respond to
the situations what we can do is open
degrees of freedom and then let the
situation you know help us self-organize
the action and so of course if you fully
control the situation such that you know
there's only two action choices or
something like that and you know
everything else is also pretty like
fixed well then you can get people to
behave like you know like they are
reactive systems almost and then things
are replicable but you might just lose
completely what's interesting about
people in the first place and so we
might have to think turn things around
and just say how do we operationalize
this variability in such a way that
rather than throwing it out or trying to
control it away we kind of like take it
as that's the marker of the person
actually making a difference here in the
task and you know like in physics
similar Revolution happened right there
was a lot of annoyance before quantum
physics came around of like why are we
getting this interference and so on and
it took a while for people to accept
that actually the way forward is to just
accept this uncertainty and
operationalize it and work with it and
get equations to work with it and then
suddenly you know everything you know
we've got the most precise signs in our
hands and but it had this you know this
is this strange switch where we suddenly
had to realize that the kind of
uncertainty was not an artifact of us uh
you know not observing things in the
right way but it was a property of the
phenomenon itself that we were trying to
understand and I think we need to do the
same thing for people and agents more
generally
and this is the classical anomaly in the
kunian Paradigm change which is it's
it's not that normal science is unaware
of the future Paradigm it's that it has
a error variance explanation we made the
partition between signal and noise as we
know it today and
that's noise which means we can describe
it with the gaussian which means it has
all these nice mathematical properties
and so so it has this kind of empirical
feel
of a total statistical model which can
be convincing but as were the total
statistical models of epicycles and
pre-quantum photoelectric phenomena
yeah you're right so and I think one one
of the things that uh I mean people I
think were always frustrated by you know
the large error bars and so on right um
and we can we can handle with them but
you know we prefer not to have them
um but I think the switch wasn't
possible yet because we didn't have a
good grasp of why there should be this
uncertainty like what explains it where
does it come from when should we expect
it and when not under what conditions
and how can we formalize it and
operationalize it and measure it so I
hope eruption Theory points a little bit
in that direction by saying hey for
example if you look at neural entropy in
the brain maybe it's actually you know
partially picking up on the subjective
involvement of making it that's making a
difference here and how the behavior or
the brain you know processes activity in
that case you know
um it's not just that we're anymore like
looking at the error bars but now it's
becoming something in itself that's of
interest to us and that we want to study
and understand so I hopefully you know
it kind of like can and you know
facilitate the power because if you
don't have another alternative well
you're stuck with just the error bars
right but yeah I think we're seeing like
the light at the other end of the tunnel
that maybe we can head towards from now
on
um one joke and then I'll read a comment
from the chat and then you can give some
closing thoughts uh the joke uh formerly
known as error bars now known as
motivation bars
um
okay I'll read it I'll read a comment
from um the chat and then you can give
any just any reflection or any closing
thoughts or next steps so um IA Roland
Rodriguez wrote
I think uh if all behaviors described as
a gentle are just products of a causal
chain of interactions and exchanges in
and out costs then there isn't this free
leap from nowhere the modeling of
organisms doesn't seem to be able to
account for this Gap in the mechanical
unfolding of energy flow where an a
priori is not an empirical sedimentation
and habituation
Pere also means to impose so one in one
question is is life hard to model
because it imposes priors seemingly from
nowhere as regards causal Dynamics
within the infinite encapsulation of
blankets I.E like the opening question
regarding the reduction of action to
Mechanical motion is the imposition of
vital priors hard to account for in
mechanistic immersionist modeling
wow there's a lot to impact there now
let me think so there was a mention of
uh energy so this is something that uh
I'm very keenly working on at the moment
and I think I just mentioned in passing
but if we think about eruptions as a
disordering consequence then you know
let's say uh this is just a kind of
thought experiment but let's say that
you know we can look at a particle
moving through space uh somewhere in
your body as part of some sort of
material flow right and that eruption
happens at that point and that location
um what would it look like from the
point of view of measuring this particle
well suddenly it would become
unpredictable right instead of just
moving forward it was just move in some
arbitrary configuration because it's no
longer constrained or only constrained
by the kind of forces that kept it
straight in the beginning and that's
basically an increase in disorder from
the point of view of the system which
means that whatever energy was contained
in that particle now is no longer
available for for doing work
um and so one interesting implication
which is still totally crazy and I'm
even almost scared to say it is that
mental work costs energy just like you
know physical work or mechanical work
and both of them cause work as cause
energy but not for the same reason so
it's not that mental work costs energy
because ultimately it's just another
form of mechanical work it is its own
drain on energy according to this idea
now
that might be a very small change you
know maybe it's not even detectable or
it could be a big one
who knows I mean you know the the brain
is the most energy expensive tissue of
the entire or like body so who knows
like whether all the energy budgets add
up the way that we expect them to I
guess that's like you know some
interesting empirical uh hypothesis that
could be you know somewhere looked at
um
and what was the other one about the
about the imposition and the priors and
so on so yeah so I've kind of left out
the origin story a little bit in the
European series I mean I gave the kind
of an active story of why should we
think that organisms have an intrinsic
perspective and why they're different
why living beings are different from
other kinds of power from equilibrium
systems
um but I actually want eruption Theory
to be independent of that a little bit
you know you know that's my preferred
way of getting to an agent you know for
me that's in a compelling story but you
can have any kind of story you want uh
and you could still plug in eruption
Theory at the point of saying now that
I've got an agent how does that agent
make a difference to the material basis
that's giving rise to it and then
eruption C we can help you understand
those those links so
um I guess one more way of thinking
about this in terms of a more
cosmological side is that if eruptions
are on the right track and are actually
a genuine source of entropy in the
organism that can't be reduced to other
sources of entropy well it increases
entropy production so that means life
due to its active regulation due to its
agency produces more entropy than
non-life in the sense of other far from
equilibrium systems like a convection
role or something like that which is a
popular example for let's say ecological
psychology to show that increased heat
transfer in actually has organizing
Tendencies you know so if you have
things rolling like this heat can flow
more easily from the pan into the air
and top
okay but if it's living and it's
actively regulating those flows it will
produce even more entropy and so if we
think of the general tendency of the
universe towards an increased entropy
production then living systems become
actually kind of natural consequence of
that unfolding in the sense that they're
adding another level of complexity on
top of other far from equilibrium
systems that is another source of Entry
production and so yeah it's kind of like
that would mean that life is kind of
expected or you know spontaneous rather
than something that is rare and weaker
than the universe
while the closing image for me is I'm
watching the water boil
and it's already far it's rolling but
jiggling it and and just helping it boil
and having that just Channel
energy right so that's a yeah that's a
metaphor for what life is all about like
you know what we're doing is just like
you know channeling the flows
well thank you very much for this
excellent guest stream I hope that the
work is well received in your Journeys
and please always feel welcome to um
come back when the time is right
okay great thank you so much for having
me that was a lot of fun awesome thank
you Tom farewell all right thank you
bye-bye bye